<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LiteraryWork Author="" Title="" Type="">Rupert Brooke was both fair to see and winning in his ways.  There was
at the first contact both <emotion type="Happiness">bloom</emotion> and charm; and most of all there was life.
To use the word his friends describe him by, he was "vivid".
This vitality, though manifold in expression, is felt primarily
in his sensations -- surprise mingled with delight --

    "One after one, like tasting a sweet food."

This is life's "first fine rapture".  It <place context="Office">makes</place> him patient to
name over those <emotion type="Nice">myriad</emotion> things (each of which seems like a fresh discovery)
curious but potent, and above all common, that he "loved", --
he the "Great Lover".  Lover of what, then?  Why, of

    "White plates and cups clean-gleaming,
    Ringed with blue lines," --

and the like, through thirty <emotion form="Comedy">lines</emotion> of exquisite words; and he is captivated
by the multiple brevity of these vignettes of sense, keen, momentary,
ecstatic with the morning dip of youth in the wonderful stream.
The poem is a catalogue of vital sensations and "dear names" as well.
"All these have been my loves."

The spring of these emotions is the natural body, but it sends pulsations
far into the spirit.  The feeling rises in direct observation,
but it is soon aware of the "outlets of the sky".
He sees objects practically unrelated, and links <action type="Awake">them</action> in strings;
or he sees <action type="Awake">them</action> pictorially; or, he sees pictures immersed as it were
in an atmosphere of thought.  When the process is complete,
the thought suggests the picture and is its origin.
Then the Great Lover revisits the bottom of the monstrous world,
and imaginatively and thoughtfully recreates that strange under-sea,
whose glooms and gleams and muds are well known to him as
a strong and delighted swimmer; or, at the last, drifts through the dream
of a South Sea lagoon, still with a philosophical question in his mouth.
Yet one can hardly speak of "completion".  These are real first flights.
What we have in this volume is not so much a work of art
as an artist in his birth trying the wings of genius.

The poet loves his new-found element.  He clings to mortality;
to life, not thought; or, as he puts it, to the concrete, --
let the abstract "go pack!"  "There's little comfort in the wise," he ends.
But in the unfolding of his precocious spirit, the literary control
comes uppermost; his boat, finding its keel, swings to the helm of mind.
How should it be otherwise for a youth well-born, well-bred,
in college air?  Intellectual primacy showed itself to him
in many wandering "loves", fine lover that he was; but in the end
he was an intellectual lover, and the magnet seems to have been
especially powerful in the ghosts of the men of "wit", Donne, Marvell --
erudite lords of language, poets in another world than ours,
a less "ample ether", a less "divine air", our fathers thought,
but poets of "eternity".  A quintessential drop of intellect
is apt to be in poetic blood.  How Platonism fascinates the poets,
like a shining bait!  Rupert Brooke will have none of it;
but at a turn of the verse he is back at it, examining, tasting, refusing.
In those alternate drives of the thought in his South Sea idyl
(clever as tennis play) how he slips from phenomenon to idea and reverses,
happy with either, it seems, "were t'other dear charmer away".
How bravely he tries to free himself from the cling of earth,
at the close of the "Great Lover"!  How little he succeeds!
His muse knew only earthly tongues, -- so far as he understood.

Why this persistent cling to mortality, -- with its quick-coming cry
against death and its heaped anathemas on the transformations of decay?
It is the old story once more: -- the vision of the first poets,
the world that "passes away".  The poetic eye of Keats saw it, --

               "Beauty that must die,
    And Joy whose hand is ever at his lips
    Bidding adieu."

The reflective mind of Arnold meditated it, --

                    "the world that seems
    To lie before us like a land of dreams,
    So various, so beautiful, so new,
    Hath really neither joy, nor love, nor light,
    Nor certitude, nor peace, nor help for pain." --

So Rupert Brooke, --

                         "But the best I've known,
    Stays here, and changes, breaks, grows old, is blown
    About the winds of the world, and fades from brains
    Of living men, and dies.
                                 Nothing remains."

And yet, --

    "Oh, never a doubt but somewhere I shall wake;"

again, --

                                   "the light,
    Returning, shall give back the golden hours,
    Ocean a windless level. . . ."

again, best of all, in the last word, --

    "Still may Time hold some golden space
     Where I'll unpack that scented store
    Of song and flower and sky and face,
     And count, and touch, and turn <action type="Awake">them</action> o'er,
    Musing upon them."

He cannot forego his sensations, that "box of compacted sweets".
He even forefeels a ghostly landscape where two shall go wandering
through the night, "alone".  So the faith that broke its chrysalis
in the first disillusionment of boyhood, in "Second Best",
beautiful with the burden of Greek lyricism, ends triumphant
with the spirit still unsubdued. --

    "Proud, then, clear-eyed and laughing, go to greet
    Death as a friend."

So go, "with unreluctant tread".  But in the disillusionment of beauty
and of love there is an older tone.  With what bitter savor, with what
grossness of diction, caught from the Elizabethan and satirical elements
in his culture, he spends anger in words!  He reacts, he rebels, he storms.
A dozen poems hardly exhaust his gall.  It is not merely
that beauty and joy and love are transient, now, but in their going
they are corrupted into their opposites, -- ugliness, pain, indifference.
And his anger once stilled by speech, what lassitude follows!

Life, in this volume, is hardly less evident by its ecstasy
than by its collapse.  It is a book of youth, sensitive, vigorous, sound;
but it is the fruit of intensity, and bears the traits.
The search for solitude, the relief from crowds, the open door into nature;
the sense of flight and escape; the repeated thought of safety,
the insistent fatigue, the cry for sleep; -- all these bear confession
in their faces.  "Flight", "Town and Country", "The Voice", are eloquent
of what they leave untold; and the climax of "Retrospect", --

    "And I should sleep, and I should sleep," --

or the sestet of "Waikiki", or the whole fainting sonnet
entitled "A Memory", belong to the nadir of vitality.  At moments
weariness set in like a spiritual tide.  I associate, too, with such moods,
psychologically at least, his visions of the "arrested moment", as in
"Dining-Room Tea", -- a sort of trance state -- or in the pendant sonnet.
Analogous moods are not infrequent in the great poets.  Rupert Brooke
seems to have faltered, nervously, at times; these poems mirror faithfully
such moments.  But even when the image of life, imaginative or real,
falters so, how essentially vital it still is, and clothed in an exquisite
body of words like the traditional "rainbow hues of the dying fish"!
For I cannot express too strongly my admiration of the literary sense
of this young poet, and my delight in it.  "All these have been my loves,"
he says, if I may repeat the phrase; but he seems to have loved the words,
as much as the things, -- "dear names", he adds.  The born man of letters
speaks there.  So, when his pulse is at its lowest,
he cannot forget the beautiful surface of his South Sea idyls
or of versified English gardens and lanes.  He cared as much
for the expression as for the thing, which is what <place context="Office">makes</place> a man of letters.
So fixed is this habit that his art, truly, is independent
of his bodily state.  In his poems of "collapse" as in those of "ecstasy"
he seems to me equally master of his mood, -- like those poets who are
"for all time".  His literary skill in verse was ripe, how long so ever
he might have to live.
</LiteraryWork>
